Guide to the Pearson Family Papers, 1875-1930
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Pearson Family papers 1875-1930
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Pearson family.
1.5 Linear Feet 1125 Items
Family based in Morganton, North Carolina, in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century.
Collection includes family correspondence, miscellaneous receipts and financial documents, and an account ledger kept by Laura Pearson Ray detailing her financial expenses between 1899 and 1929. Subjects include courtship, family news and events, illnesses, the death and mourning of a child, World War I, and United Daughters of the Confederacy activities. Locations discussed or referenced include Morganton, Fayetteville, Durham, and Chapel Hill, North Carolina, and Clinton, South Carolina.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Pearson Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a series of gifts between 1998-2012.
Biographical and Historical Note
The Pearson Family Papers stem from the letters and ledger of Laura Pearson Ray, a daughter of Robert C. and Jane S. Pearson of Morganton, North Carolina. Laura Pearson corresponded with and eventually married Neill W. Ray, a Civil War veteran. The couple's first child, Neill W. Ray, Jr., died in infancy in 1879. Their second son, Donald Ray, was born in 1888. The family settled in Fayetteville, where Neill W. Ray, Sr., was a lawyer and influential citizen. Neill W. Ray died in 1899. Donald became a lawyer as well and served on the Chief of Artillery staff in Washington, D.C.
Laura's sister, Jennie S. Pearson Tate, married Samuel McDowel Tate. The couple had several children, including Alexander, Claudia, Wilhelmina, Sue Virginia, and Irene. Less is known about the Tate family, although they seem to have been based in Morganton, N.C.
Learn more about the provenance of this collection and the genealogical research of this family at "Messages of a Hidden Past," a website managed by Myrtle N. Bridges.
Collection Overview
The collection has been arranged into series of Correspondence, Financial Materials, and Miscellaneous. The Correspondence series, the largest of the three, includes family correspondence that has been sorted by family member. Correspondents include Laura Pearson Ray, Donald Ray, Wilhelmina Tate, Sue Virginia Tate, Jennie Pearson Tate, Gordan Tate, and other smaller amounts of letters from various Pearsons and Tates. Topics range widely, but notable subjects include courtship, particularly between Laura Pearson and Neill W. Ray; Reconstruction conditions and North Carolina politics (Governor Zebulon Vance, the state's Reconstruction governor, was Laura's cousin); family health; condolence letters following the death of Jennie's son in 1902; travel, particularly Donald Ray's accounts of his trip through Europe in 1912; World War I, including letters from Gordon Tate while he served in France; and various financial matters.
The Financial Materials series contains miscellaneous receipts, again sorted by family member. Most notable in this series is the account ledger kept by Laura Pearson Ray following her husband's death in 1899, which includes entries about Cumberland County families, including Ray, Lilly, McKay, Monroe, Thornton, Broadfoot, Pearson, Hale, McRae, Haigh, Remsburge, and more. This series also includes a typescript copy of the ledger, for research purposes, which also details its known provenance.
The Miscellaneous Materials series contains several miscellaneous notes and receipts, including a bound constitution from the Ladies Memorial Association of Burke County. Also included are Laura Pearson Ray's sewing patterns and some fabric, and several newsclippings with Tate family obituaries.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Ray, Laura Pearson
Pearson family
Ray family
Tate family
Governors -- North Carolina
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- North Carolina
North Carolina -- Social life and customs -- 1865- .
North Carolina -- History -- 19th century
North Carolina -- History -- 20th century
North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
Fayetteville (N.C.) -- History
Tate, Jennie Pearson
Pearson, Ann Elizabeth
Tate, Irene
Pearson, Claudia
Ray, Neill W.
Ray, Donald
World War, 1914-1918
Clinton (S.C.)
Morganton (N.C.) -- History
Durham (N.C.)
Europe -- Description and travel -- 20th century
Children -- Death
United Daughters of the Confederacy -- North Carolina
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1875-1923, (2 boxes)
  The Correspondence series includes family letters that have been sorted by family member. Correspondents include Laura Pearson Ray, Donald Ray, Wilhelmina Tate, Sue Virginia Tate, Jennie Pearson Tate, Gordan Tate, and other smaller amounts of letters from various Pearsons and Tates. Topics range widely, but notable subjects include courtship, particularly between Laura Pearson and Neill W. Ray; Reconstruction conditions and North Carolina politics (Governor Zebulon Vance, the state's Reconstruction governor, was Laura's cousin); family health; condolence letters following the death of Jennie's son in 1902; travel, particularly Donald Ray's accounts of his trip through Europe in 1912; World War I, including letters from Gordon Tate while he served in France; and various financial matters.
  - Laura Pearson Ray, 1875-1878 March, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Laura Pearson Ray, 1898-1902 and undated (Box 1)
  - Donald Ray to Laura Pearson Ray, re: European trip, 1912 July-August (Box 1)
  - Wilhelmina Tate, 1897-1911, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Sue Virginia Tate, 1896-1923, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Jennie Pearson Tate, 1899-1902 (Box 2)
  - Ann Elizabeth Pearson, 1901-1904 (Box 2)
  - Claudia Pearson, 1902 May-June (Box 2)
  - Irene Tate, 1902-1923 (Box 2)
  - Gordon Tate, re: World War I, 1918-1919 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Tate family letters, 1889-1922 (Box 2)
- Financial Materials, 1899-1930, (2 boxes)
  The Financial Materials series contains miscellaneous receipts, sorted by family member. Most notable in this series is the account ledger kept by Laura Pearson Ray following her husband's death in 1899, which includes entries about Cumberland County families, including Ray, Lilly, McKay, Monroe, Thornton, Broadfoot, Pearson, Hale, McRae, Haigh, Remsburge, and more. This series also includes a typescript copy of the ledger, for research purposes, which also details its known provenance.
  - Laura Pearson Ray deeds and rents, 1899-1907 (Box 2)
  - Wilhelmina Tate receipts, 1900-1912 and undated (Box 2)
  - Sue Virginia Tate, 1906-1930 (Box 2)
  - Laura Pearson Ray checkbook registers, 1905-1926 (Box 2)
  - Laura Pearson Ray Ledger, 1899-1929 (Box 3)
  - Laura Pearson Ray Ledger typescript and inserts (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Materials, 1898-1902 and undated, (1 box)
  The Miscellaneous Materials series contains several miscellaneous notes and receipts, including a bound constitution from the Ladies Memorial Association of Burke County. Also included are Laura Pearson Ray's sewing patterns and some fabric, and several newsclippings with Tate family obituaries.
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3)
  - Laura Pearson Ray sewing patterns and fabric, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Tate family obituaries, 1898-1902 (Box 3)